这节课以及下节课 我要为你们展示两种很智能
In this segment and the next, I wanna show
you two very cute attacks on deployed
对认证加密系统的攻击 但首先让我们来快速的回顾下
authenticated encryption systems. But
first let's do a quick recap. So recall
回想下 认证加密系统保证了面对选择明文攻击的安全性以及密文完整性
that authenticated encryption means that
the system provides CPA security plus
并且认证加密面对一个主动攻击的敌手
cipher text integrity. And authenticated
encryption means that we can preserve
也具有保密性 不仅如此 攻击者
confidentiality in the presence of an
active adversary, and moreover, the
不可能做到不被察觉的修改密文信息 我们可以说
adversary can't modify the cipher text in
any way without being detected. We also
认证加密技术抵御了这些非常强大的选择密文攻击
showed that authenticated encryption
prevents these very powerful chosen cipher
不幸的是 认证加密也有一个非常明显的缺陷
text attacks. Unfortunately, authenticated
encryption has a pretty significant
就是它非常不容易实现 假如你没有正确的实现认证加密技术
limitation in that it simply can't help a
bad implementation. If you implement
那你的实现可能面对主动攻击时非常的脆弱
authenticated encryption incorrectly, then
your implementation will be vulnerable to
我们来看下标准的结构 前面我提到过
active attacks. And then we looked at
standards constructions. I mentioned these
这三个标准规定了认证加密技术 并且我想指出
three standards that provide authenticated
encryption. And I want to point out, when
当你在练习中要用到认证加密时 你应该会用到
you need to use authenticated encryption
in practice, you should just be using one
这三个标准 而不应该实现你自己的认证加密
of these three standards. You shouldn't
try to implement authenticated encryption
所以 我希望我在这一节中所讲的能说服你们
by yourself, and I hope that the attack
that I'll show you in this segment
不要做自己来做认证加密 而是使用GCM,CCM,EAX中的一个
convinces you that this is not something
you should do yourself. Just use one of
我们先来做一个大致上的了解吧
GCM, CCM or EAX. However, it's good for
you to know that in general, when you want
当你想要提供一个认证加密时 正确的做法就是加密 然后消息验证码
to provide authenticated encryption, the
correct way to do things is encrypt, then
因为无论你怎么结合加密和MAC算法
MAC, because then no matter which
encryption and MAC algorithms you combine.
结局都会被认证加密 然后再次正确地使用加密和MAC算法
The result will be authenticated
encryption, again assuming the encryption
好吧 我们再来看一个关于安全传输层协议记录协议的攻击
and Mac algorithm are implemented
correctly. Okay, so let's look at a very
尤其是使用加密块链模式来加密的时候
acute attack on the TLS record protocol.
In particular, when CBC encryption is
我简要说明下TLS加密是怎么工作的
used. Let me just briefly remind you that
the way TLS decryption works, is, first of
首先 一个输入的密文是由CBC解密的
all, an incoming cipher text is CBC
decrypted. Then the next thing that
然后这个实现将要检查填充格式是否正确
happens is the implementation will check
if the pad has the correct format. For
举个例子 假如填充的长度是5 那格式就应该是55555
example, if the pad is of length five, the
format should be 55555. And if it's not of
如果填充格式不正确的话 这个密文就会被丢弃
the correct format. Then the cipher text
is rejected. So this basically checks that
所以基本上都要检查解密记录的最后是否包含正确的填充
the ending of the decrypted record
contains the correct pad. And then if the
如果填充正确的话 下一步就是检查消息认证码和标签
pad has the correct format, then the next
thing that happens is that the MAC is
如果标签不正确的话 记录也要被丢弃
checked, the tag is checked. And if the
tag turns out to be incorrect, again, the
如果标签正确 那么剩下的数据就会被看作被认证了
record is rejected. If the tag is valid,
then the remaining data is considered to
并且会提交给应用程序 那么我想指出的就是
be authentic and is given to the
application. So what I wanted to point out
有两种错误在TLS解密中 一个是填充错误
is there are two types of errors in TLS
decryption. One is a padding error and one
另一个是消息验证码错误 这很重要 因为你的对手不知道
is a MAC error. And it turns out it's very
important that the adversary not be told
发生的是那种错误 让我来解释下
which of these errors occurred. And let me
briefly explain why. So, suppose an
想象下 一个攻击者可以区分这两种错误 就是说他可以找到
attacker can actually differentiate the
two types of errors. In other words, he
发生的是填充错误还是消息认证码错误 我们称为填充预言机
can tell if a pad error occurred, or a Mac
error occurred. The result is what we call
现在 想象这个攻击者截获了一个确定的密文
the padding oracle. Bcause now, imagine
the adversary has a certain cipher text
并且他想要尝试破解这段密文
that it intercepted. And it wants to try
and decrypt that cipher text. What it
他可能要做的就是把这段密文提交给服务器
could do, is it could take that cipher
text as is, and submit it to the server.
服务器会解密这段密文然后看填充格式是否正确
The server is gonna decrypt the cipher
text and then look to see if the pad has
如果填充格式不正确 我们就得到了一种错误
the correct format. If the pad doesn't
have the correct format, we'll get one
如果填充有一个正确的格式 那很可能就是
type of error. If the pad has the correct
format, it's very likely since this is
敌手自己捏造了一个随机密文 很可能
just some random cipher text that the
adversary concocted himself, it's very
消息认证码就是不正确的 然后对手就会得知一个消息认证码错误
likely the mac will be incorrect, and then
the adversary will observe a mac error. So
如果填充无效 我们会看到填充错误 反之 如果填充正确 我们会看到
if the pad is invalid, we'll see a pad
error, whereas if the pad is valid we'll
消息认证码错误 结果就是 攻击者 在提交密文给服务器后
see a mac error. As a result, the
adversary, after submitting the cipher
他就可以知道解密后的密文最后一个字节是否是一个有效的填充
text to the server, the adversary can tell
whether the last bytes in the decrypted
换句话说 他会知道解密后的密文最后的字节是否是
cipher text have a valid pad or not. In
other words, whether the last bites in the
1 2-2 3-3-3 4-4-4-4 等等这样的形式
decrypted cipher text are end with one. Or
2-2, or 3-3-3, or 4-4-4-4, and so on. So
所以敌手就可以得知解密后的密文 仅仅通过把密文
the adversary learns something about the
decrypted cipher text, just by submitting
提交给服务器 那么 这就是一个非常好玩的例子 叫做选择密文攻击
the cipher text to the server. So this is
a beautiful example of what's called a
在来一遍 你把密文提交给服务器
chosen cipher text attack. Where again,
the address that you submit the cipher
然后攻击者就可以得知最后的明文
text and then he gets to learn something
about the resulting plain text. And now
那么问题来了 他是否能使用这些信息来完全破解一个密文？
the question is whether he can use that
information to completely decrypt a given
让我来展示下 一个填充预言机是怎么完全破解
cipher text. And I want to show you that a
padding oracle can actually be used to
一个给定的密文的 不过在这之前我再说下
completely decrypt a given cipher text.
But before I say that, I want to remind
TLS的较老的版本 它会在送还给窥窃者的警告信息中
you that older versions of TLS. Actually
leaked the type of error simply in the
泄露错误的类型 发送出不同种类的警告信息
alert message that was sent back to the
peer. Different types of alerts were sent
依赖于发生的不同种类的错误 这种攻击一产生
depending on which type of error occurred.
As soon as this attack came out, SSL
SSL就只报告同一种类的错误了 所以
implementations simply always reported the
same type of error, so just looking at the
只通过看警告 敌方已经不能得知错误类型了
alert type wouldn't tell the adversary
which error occurred. Nevertheless, there
无论如何 还是有一个填充预言机 我来解释下
was still a padding oracle. So let me
explain why. So this was observed by Canvel
比如 这被Canvel发现了 他察觉到
et. al. Canvel et. al. realized that
the way TLS decryption is implemented is
TLS解密的第一步是先解密记录 然后再检查填充
first of all, the record is decrypted,
then the pad is checked, and if the pad is
如果填充无效 解密中止 一个错误发生 如果填充有效
invalid, decryption is aborted and an
error is generated. If the pad is valid.
继续检查消息验证码 然后如果验证码无效的话 解密中止 再生成一个错误
Then the Mac is checked. And then if the
Mac is invalid, decryption is aborted, and
这样做的结果 就是会产生一个时序攻击
an error is generated. As a result, this
causes a timing attack. You realize that
你这样想 如果填充无效 很快就会发送一个警告信息
if pad is invalid, then the alert message
is sent very quickly. And you notice here,
注意这里 在第21毫秒的时候 密文被丢弃
that, in fact, you see that, within 21
milliseconds, the cipher text is rejected.
然而 如果填充是有效的 就需要检查MAC
However, if the pad is valid. Then now the
mac needs to be checked, and when it's
然后 当发现MAC是无效时 警告就会同时产生
discovered to be invalid, the alert is
only generated at that point. In other
就是说 在这种情况下 警告会晚一点产生
words, then in that case it takes a little
bit longer until the alert is generated,
这里 你会看到 大概平均花费23毫秒时间
and you see that on average this takes
about 23 milliseconds. So even though the
所以 即使收到相同的警告 敌手还是可以通过观察警告信息
same alert is sent back to the peer. The
adversary can simply observe the time
生成的时间 如果时间比较短 就是填充无效
until the alert message is generated. If
the time is short, it knows the pad was
如果时间比较长 就是填充有效 消息认证码无效
invalid. If the time is long, it knows the
pad was valid, but the Mac was invalid.
结果就是 敌方仍然可以通过填充预言机来判断
And as a result the adversary still has a
padding oracle that can tell it whether
填充是否有效 现在我们来看下怎么使用填充预言机
the pad was valid or invalid. So now let's
see how to use a padding oracle. So I
我先声明下 如果攻击者有一个确定的密文C 那么
claim that if the attacker has a certain
cipher text C, he can completely decrypt
他就可以用填充预言机来破解密文 我们来看看他是如果做到的
the cipher text just using the padding
oracle. So let's see how to do it. And
举个例子 想象下他想要得到M1 就是密文第二个分组
just as an example, suppose he wants to
obtain M1, in other words, a decryption of
解密出的消息 那么我们来看看他会用到什么
the second block of the cipher text. So
let's see what he would use. So here we
这里我们知道攻击者截获的密文 并且下面正好是
have the cipher text that the attacker
intercepted. And this just happens to be
这段密文解密出的消息 我把这些写下来的原因是我想让你
the decryption of that cipher text. And
the reason I wrote this down is I wanted
记住分组块链密码是如何解密的 一个密文分组直接
you to remember how CBC decryption works.
So you should keep in mind that one cipher
和解密后的下一个密文分组异或
text block is directly XOR into
the decryption of the next cipher text
那么 攻击者想要得到这部分的明文
block. Okay, so the adversary here wants
to basically learn just this part of the
那他将要做的就是 首先他先丢弃C2
plain text. So, here's what he's gonna do.
So first of all he's going to throw away
那么最后一个分组就变成了C1 这也是他想要破解的
C2 so that, that last block really is just
C1, which is the one he's interested in
我们假设 他有一个猜想G 作为M1的最后一个字节
decrypting. Now let's suppose that he has
a certain guess, G, for the last byte of
就是说 他猜测了最后一个字节G
M1, in other words, he just has a guess
for this very, very, very last byte. G is
G的值是在0到255之间 然后攻击者接下来会这么做
a value between zero and 255. What the
attacker will do is the following, he will
他会用C0的最后一个字节来异或G的值然后再异或01.
XOR the value G XOR 01 into the last byte
of the block C0, the previous block. Yes
他所做的就是用前面这个分组的最后一个字节来
so all he did is he took the last byte of
the previous block and XOR that with
异或他的猜测G再异或01 我们想想看如果这两个
his guess XOR 01. Now lets think for
just a second and see what happens when
分组密码被解密了会发生什么 C0是会得到解密
this two block cipher text is decrypted.
Well C0 is gonna get decrypted to whatever
尽管其解密只会得到一些垃圾 但我们不在乎
its decrypted to that's just gonna be some
garbage that we don't care about but, now
现在如果c1被解密 最后一个字节是要和修改后的CO进行异或
when C1 is decrypted the last byte is
gonna be XOR with this modified C0,
和明文的最后一个字节 也将被异或
and the result the last byte of the plain
text. Is gonna be also XORed with this
用我们插入到C0的值 这里进入实际的明文
extra value that we stuck into C0. So
what goes in here is the actual original
M1中最后一个字节 但是现在它将要异或g异或0x01
last byte in the plain text M1. But now it
gets XORed with G XOR zero X zero one. So
现在看我讲的这里 如果为m1的最后一比特猜测的g值是
now you see where I'm going with this. If
the guess G for the last byte of M1 is
正确的 然后这两个项将彼此抵消 最后一比特异或g结果就是0
correct, then these two guys will cancel
one another. Last byte XOR G is just zero.
我们将得到明文的最后一比特是0x01 顺便提一下
And what we'll get is the last byte of the
plaintext is just 0x01. I should mention,
0x01意味着十六进制记数法中的01 所以这只是
by the way, 0x01 just means hex notation
for 01. So literally this is just a one
一个数量的一个字节表示 好 我们再看 如果我们对m1的
byte representation of the number one.
Good. So, again, what this means, is if
最后一比特的猜测正确 这意味着我们得到了一个
our guess for the last byte of M1 is
correct, then we get a pad that's well
已形成的填充 这只是数字1是个已经完成的填充 因此
formed. It's just a number one. The number
one is a well formed pad, and therefore,
填充的是有效的 填充预言机会显示填充是有效的 如果猜测
the pad is valid. And the padding oracle
will say the pad is valid. If the guess is
不对 我们会得到一个不等于1的值 那我们很有
incorrect then we'll get a value here
that's not equal to one and then it's very
可能会得到一个无效的填充 因此 填充机会显示
likely that we have an invalid pad. And as
a result the padding worker will say the
填充无效 我们再来看 如果我们对m1最后一比特的猜测
pad is invalid. So again you see that if
our guess for the last byte of M1 is
正确 我们会发现g事实上是正确的猜测 然而如果猜测
correct, we learn that G was in fact a
correct guess. Whereas if our guess is
不对 那g同样是错误的猜测
incorrect, then we learn that G is an
incorrect guess. So what the attacker is
所攻击者要做的是 他会创建修改后的密文 我们注意到
gonna do is he's gonna create his modified
cipher text. You notice he only modifies
他只是修改了密文的第二个分组 我们要把这个发送到填充预言机
the second block of the cipher text. We're
gonna send this to the padding oracle and
基于填充预言机的输出 我们将知道最后一比特
then based on the results of the padding
oracle, we learn whether the last byte is
是否等于g  这里我们会重复使用g从0到255
equal to G or not. Well, now we can simply
repeat this again and again for G from
从0到255 这基本上需要256次选择密文查询 其实
zero to 255. This basically requires 256
chosen cipher text queries. Actually, I
我觉得我们平均只需做128次选择密文求平方 直到
guess on average we'll only have to do 128
chosen ciphers and squares until we find
找到正确的g 然后我们会得到m1的最后一比特 那现在我们知道了m1的最后一比特
the right G. Then, we learn the last byte
of M1. Well, so now we know the last byte
我认为我们现在可以使用相同的过程来得知M1的
of M1. I claim that we can now use the
exact same process to learn the second to
倒数第二字节 我来问你们 当我们要得知m1的倒数第二个字节时
last byte of M1. Let me ask you, what pad
are we gonna use to learn the second to
我们该用什么填充 令人惊讶的是 我们不用刚才用到的
last byte of M1? Well, it shouldn't be
surprising that, instead of just using the
一个字节填充 而是用一个两个字节的填充机制 就是2-2
pad containing the byte one, we're gonna
use a two byte pad containing the bytes
这也是一种成熟的填充机制 现在我们可以确定 因为我们知道了
2-2. That's a well formed pad. And now we
can always make sure because we know the
m1的最后一比特 当我们进行异或运算的时候 我们能很肯定
last byte of m1, when we do our XORing trick
we can always make sure that the last byte
其实明文的最后一比特是02 现在我们可以猜测m2的倒数第二比特
of the plain text is in fact 02 and now we
can guess the second to last byte of m2 by
通过大量的尝试g的值 直到找到合适的填充 其实
simply trying lots of values in g until we
find one that makes the pad, in fact, be
就是0202 通过对预言机发行256个额外的查询 我们就能
0202. And by issuing 256 additional
queries to the padding oracle we will get
得到m1的倒数第二个比特 接下来就是一次又一次的迭代
to learn the second to last byte of m1.
And now we can iterate this again and
由于分组的长度是16比特  16次的256查询后
again, and basically since the length of
the block is sixteen bytes after sixteen
我们会得到所有的值 所以这是一个非常重要的攻击
times 256 queries. We get to learn all of
them one. So this is a pretty significant
它可以解密TLS的记录分组 你们所知道的
attack that is able to decrypt blocks of
the TLS record. So those of you who know
那些TLS的内部工作人员抱怨说这个攻击不会实现
the inner workings of TLS should complain
that this attack isn't gonna work. The
问题是当TLS收到一个坏的填充或者坏的Mac 就会
problem is that when TLS receives a record
with a bad pad or a bad Mac, it shuts down
关闭连接 再次协商一个新密钥 因此 攻击者现在
the connection, and renegotiates a new
key. As a result, the attacker is now
正在尝试破解用旧密钥加密的密文 但是那个密钥
stuck with a cipher text encrypted using
an old key. And that key is no longer used
已经不用了 所以也不能提交更多的查询 对TLS 其实只能
anywhere, so it cannot submit any more
queries. So with TLS, basically, it can
提交一个查询 就是这样 即便是一个查询也能给攻击者
only submit one query, and that's it. Even
a single query still leaks information
泄露很多关于密文的信息 但是不会暴露秘闻的整个
about the plain text to the attacker. But
it doesn't expose the entire plain text
m1分组 然而这个攻击很智能 只要有这样的一个错误的
block m1. However this attack is so acute
that whenever there's a mistake like this
协议将会有一些设置出现 在这种情况下
in a protocol there will be some settings
in which it comes up and in this case the
设置imap服务器的情况 IMAP是一种从IMAP邮件服务
setting is in the case of an imap server.
So imap is a popular protocol for reading
读邮件的流行的协议 通常都是保护IMAP协议
email from an imap email server, and it's
very common to protect the imap protocol
运行在TLS协议的顶部  现在 结果变成了IMAP  每5分钟
by running it on top of a tls protocol.
Now, it turns out an imap. Every five
IMAP客户会连接到IMAP服服务器 检查是否有
minutes, the IMap client will connect to
the IMap server, and check whether there's
新邮件 其工作方式是对IMAP服务器的第一次登陆
new email. And the way it does it is by
first logging in to the IMap server, by
通过将登录名和口令都发送过去的方式 然后它继续
sending this login username password
message. And then it goes ahead and check
检查是否有新邮件到达 这就意味着每5分钟
if there's new email available. Well, what
this means is that every five minutes, the
攻击者就可以得到 尤其是一个完全相同的加密信息 我想
attacker gets an encryption of exactly the
same message in particular, I guess, an
是关于登录口令的加密信息 所以每5分钟 他就可以增加一个
encryption of the password. And so every
five minutes, it can mount one guess on
包括登录口令在内的分组 如果你的口令是8个字符长的
the block that contains the password. And
so, if your password is eight characters
攻击者只需恢复这8个字符 他会
long, the attacker simply needs to recover
those eight characters. And he's gonna
一次恢复一比特  每5分钟做一次猜测
recover them one byte at, at a time, by
doing one guess per five minutes. And so
Canvel等人发现 在数小时内 你就可以恢复出一个
Canvel et. al. showed that, within a few
hours, you can basically recover the
用户的口令 仅仅是每5分钟增加一个猜测 所以这是一个
user's password. Just by mounting one
guest every five minutes. So this is a
对TLS的实现的很重要的攻击 对此攻击的
pretty significant attack against an
implementation of TLS and the defense
防卫就是经常检查Mac 看填充是否有效
against this was to always check the Mac,
whether the pad is valid or invalid. And
因此需要相同的时间回应填充是否有效
as a result it takes the same amount of
time to respond whether the pad is valid
这消除了时间攻击 增加了攻击难度
or invalid. So this removes the timing
attack and makes this attack much harder
所以这里有两个教训 第一 你们会发现 如果TLS
to mount. So there are two lessons here.
First of all, you notice that if TLS had
使用先加密后mac 而不是先mac后加密 那这整个事件会
used encrypt then MAC, rather than MAC
then encrypt, then this whole issue would
完全没意义的 因为如果我先加密后Mac 那Mac是先检验
be completely moot, because if I encrypt
then MAC then MAC is checked first, and
然后只有先解密然后填充检验发生 当先加密后填充时
only then does decryption and pad-checking
take place. In encrypt then MAC, the
密文被丢弃 因为MAC是无效的 我们从来没有填充检查
cipher-text is discarded because the MAC
is invalid and we never even get to a pad
因此 任何篡改或获得与密文将立即丢弃
check. As a result, any tampering or gain
is with a cipher-text will be discarded
因为MAC是会失败的 第二个要记住的教训是
immediately because the MAC is simply
gonna fail. And second lesson to remember
记住我跟你们说过 Mac-then-CBC确实提供了经过认证加密
is that remember I told you that MAC-then-CBC
actually does provide authenticated
但只要如果你不透露cryption失败的原因 这样的话
encryption but only if you don't reveal
why the cryption failed. In this case the
填充墙完全摧毁了验证加密属性
padding wall will completely
destroyed the authenticating encryption
基本上我展示给你的这种攻击显示了这种模式
property and basically I showed you an
attack this shows that now this mode does
没有提供认证加密 我来问你们如下问题
not provide authenticated encryption. So
let me ask you the following question.
假设TLS不用先Mac后CBC 而是先Mac后计数
Supposing TLS instead of using MAC then
CBC, TLS did MAC then counter mode
加密填充预言机攻击任然会是有可能的吗 答案是
encryption. Would the padding oracle
attack still be possible or not? The
不可能 只是因为 计数模式不用任何
answer is it wouldn't be possible, simply
because counter-mode doesn't use any
填充 所以填充预言机攻击只会影响TLS里的CBC加密
padding at all. So this padding oracle
attack only effects CBC encryption modes
TLS也支持计数模式加密 计数的模式加密模式
in TLS. Tls also supports counter-mode
encryption, and counter-mode encryption
是不会被这些填充攻击影响 那这节课就讲到这里
modes are simply not affected by these
padding attacks. So that's the end of this
下一节课我要给你们讲另一个非常非常聪明的
segment. In the next segment I want to
show you another very, very clever attack on
对认证加密系统的攻击
authenticated encryption systems.